# Gabriel Nicolás Camargo Toledo

Mailing Address: Cra 4 # 1-82 Casa 12

Camino La Balsa

Chía, Cundinamarca, Colombia, 250001

Phone: +57-317-531-6851 Skype: gaborio123

Email: gn.camargo215@uniandes.edu.co

### Personal profile

MA in Political Science, Vanderbilt University, Nashville TN, USA. BA Political Science, Universidad de los Andes. I have 11+ years of experience in research on social science, particularly in the areas of comparative politics, political behavior, and political economy. Plus 3+ years of teaching experience on both substantive and technical topics. I am interested in topics of democracy, democratic attitudes, elections, and institutions. I have experience in designing, implementing, and analyzing public opinion surveys and integrating quantitative and qualitative evidence under the premier academic institution in Latin America; the Latin American Public Opinion Project (LAPOP). I have experience in survey research and impact evaluation and monitoring, integrating qualitative and quantitative evidence. I have the skills and interest in creating content for nontechnical audiences based on statistical evidence about political and socioeconomic phenomena. I am proficient with different computational tools for research that include Stata and R and Python. I have excellent communication skills in English and Spanish. I have shown my leadership and management skills in business, research, and student settings.

## Areas of specialization

Democracy • Democratic values • Comparative politics • Political Methodology • Elections • Political Institutions •Political behavior • Statistics • Political Methodology • Survey Analysis and Design

## Last position

Aug 2020- Apr Senior Researcher. Sensata UX Research

As a Senior Researcher at Sensata UX, my responsibilities were focused on the entire research process. I was part of the team responsible for the theoretical and methodological design of the investigations. I handled the processing and preparation of data, as well as its analysis. For analysis, I utilized descriptive graphical tools, linear regression, and hierarchical clustering techniques. I also employed Bayesian multilevel models for analyzing experiments involving discrete choice. I collaborated in the preparation of reports for clients and took part in presenting the results to them. I was also in charge of developing software in R that facilitated and consolidated data management and analysis. This allowed for improved efficiency and speed of response from the moment data was collected on the Sensata platform to the final delivery of microdata to clients, meeting their requirements. It also helped standardize the analysis performed by the research team, while remaining flexible to address the diverse methodological needs of different projects.

#### Education

B.A. in Political Science, Universidad de los Andes, Colombia M.A. in Political Science, Vanderbilt University

### Conference presentations

- "When Presidents are coaches: World Cup results affect citizens' evaluation of the government."
  With Oscar Castorena. Annual meeting of the Midwest Political Science Association. Chicago, IL,
  USA
- "Political sophistication and clarity of responsibility: understanding conditional economic vote."

  Annual meeting of the Midwest Political Science Association. Chicago, IL, USA
- "When a gender quota is (not) effective. Colombia legislative elections 2010-2014." With Bibiana Astrid Ortega. VIII Congreso latinoamericano de ciencia política. Lima, Perú.
- "Presidential Charisma and (Anti)Democratic Values in Latin America." With Alejandra Ortiz and Juan Carlos Rodríguez-Raga. Annual meeting of the Midwest Political Science Association. Chicago, IL, USA
  - "Institutions, Accountability and Conditional Economic Voting in Latin America. A Hierarchical Analysis." With Miguel García-Sanchez and Juan Carlos Rodríguez-Raga. Annual meeting of the American Political Science Association. Seattle, WA, USA

### Work in Progress

2011

- "The impact of institutions on turnout: A behavioral theory"
- "When Presidents are coaches: World Cup results affect citizens' evaluation of the government." With Oscar Castorena
- "Political sophistication and clarity of responsibility: understanding conditional economic vote."
- "When a gender quota is (not) effective. Colombia legislative elections 2010-2014." With Bibiana Ortega
- "Campaign finance in Colombia"
- "Political Knowledge and Clarity of Responsibility. Understanding the Conditional Economic Vote"

#### Other Publications

- Ortega Gómez, Bibiana Astrid & Camargo Toledo, Gabriel N. "Ley de cuotas en Colombia: Elecciones al Congreso de la República 2014-2018. (Quota law in Colombia: Elections to Congress of the Republic 2014-2018)" in *Elecciones en Colombia, 2014. ¿Representaciones Fragmentadas?* Edited by Freddy Barrero and Margarita Batlle.
  - Camargo Toledo, Gabriel N. & Rodríguez Raga, Juan Carlos. "Familias en Acción y preferencias políticas. Colombia 2010. (Familias en Accion (Colombian CCT program) and political preferences. Colombia 2010)", Apuntes de cultura política 1

### Research Experience

Short term consultant. South Asia Data Lab. World Bank.

Research Assistant, Latin American Public Opinion Project (LAPOP), Department of Political Sci-

ence, Vanderbilt University.

2014-2015 Research Assistant, Mitchell Selligson, Department of Political Science, Vanderbilt University.

Summer Research Assistant, Kristin Michelitch, Department of Political Science, Vanderbilt Uni-

versity.

2014

2016

2012

Research Assistant. Observatorio de la Democracia, Departamento de Ciencia Política, Universidad

de los Andes.

## Teaching

"Investigación cuantitativa para relaciones internacionales." Quantitative research for international

relations. Universidad Javeriana. Bogotá, Colombia.

"Seminario de investigación." Research Seminar (Undergraduate) Universidad de los Andes. Bo-

gotá, Colombia.

Teaching Assistant, Tizoc Chavez. Nature of war (Undergraduate). Vanderbilt University

Teaching Assistant, Hye Young You. Statistics 3. Maximum likelihood and causal inference (Grad-

uate). Vanderbilt University.

Teaching Assistant, Zeynep Somer-Topcu. European Union (Undergraduate). Vanderbilt Univer-

sitv.

Instructor. "Analizando la política. Racionalidad, juegos y estrategias" (Analyzing polítics. Ratio-

nality, games and strategies) (Undergraduate). Universidad Sergio Arboleda. Bogotá, Colombia.

Teaching Assistant. "Nivelación en Estadística para posgrados" (Equivalent to math camp for new

graduate students) (Graduate). Universidad de los Andes. Bogotá, Colombia.

## Professional and Dept. Service

Sponsor MUN Gimnasio Fontana, GFMUN.

2016-2017 Co-President Latin American and Caribbean Student Association. Vanderbilt University.

2016-2017 Co-Representative to the Graduate Student Council. Political Science Graduate Student Associa-

tion. Vanderbilt University.

2015-2016 Co-President. Political Science Graduate Student Association. Vanderbilt University.

#### Others

Software Advanced R, Stata y Python. Advanced Office. Basic SPSS y SAS.

Idiomas Spanish (native), English (Advanced, Toefl 115/120).

Miscellaneous Advanced Open Water Scuba Diver PADI[1cm]

Last updated: June 1, 2023 • Typeset in X-TEX